[Music]
Welcome to this Business Central launch
edition 2025 release wave 2. In this
video, we're going to talk about two
things, drill back and dynamic dimension
names for the PowerBI apps for Business
Central. Now, this sounds scary and
technical, but it is actually some
really useful features in the PowerBI
apps. So we cover these two concepts.
Drill back is for situations where you
got want to understand the a number in
in the report. What what is behind that
number? So for instance, maybe you want
to kind of have trust in the reports or
maybe you want to troubleshoot
why is like why do we have so many um
liabilities on this account and actually
want to dive into the figures.
Um the other feature is dynamic
dimension naming and that is u uh
because dimensions is a very popular
feature in business central. Um and in
the previous PowerBI apps we only had
the dimension codes and also uh only
ability to filter on global dimension 1
2 and three. So the actual names were
not present in PowerBI and we have
solved that. Um, so we're going to show
you how you can um you need to edit the
the reports, but then you can actually
get both the names and also the the
proper fields of dimensions um as
filters in your PowerBI reports. So
let's dive in and first look at
drillback.
All right. So imagine you are a
controller and uh you take a look at
your liabilities. So here's the
liability PowerBI report and um here I
have some accounts for instance this GL
account 22100 has current liabilities of
105,831.
Now remember that number because uh what
happens here is you can see in this
matrix that I now have a link and if I
choose this link this will open up a new
business central tab. So I can still go
back to where I was and this opens up
all the transactions behind that number.
Remember the number you you remember
that. Let's dive into take this list
into uh analysis mode. And uh I'll just
also show you a new cool feature here.
If I search for amount and right click
this guy here, I can scroll amount into
view. So a new feature here in 27. And
if you look at that sum here, 105 835.
That is actually the number I asked you
to uh to remember. So it's not magic
even though this is like a magic trick.
This is a drill back from PowerBI back
to business central. The second feature
is dynamic dimension naming. So um let
me show you in PowerBI
um the sales app and show how the
dimensions look uh in there with this
new feature.
All right. So here in PowerBI desktop I
have opened the sales app and
like in previous versions here are the
filters and like you can see I have
filters on global dimension one two and
that's kind of sad in a way right so
global dimension one has uh is
apparently departments I think and
global dimension two is I think it's
customer group but that's really hard
right so let so how can we fix this with
this new feature
Um what I need to do is go to data and
here I have a new table called dimension
sets where you can see we are now
loading the customer group name and the
department name. So these are the actual
global dimension one and two and that
means I can uh for instance plug in as a
filter let me just get this down here. I
could put in the customer group
as a filter here and this is now
dynamically named. So if I go up here,
customer group name actually have the
the right name of customer group as well
as the right values of this. Right? So I
can I can now filter to large business
and get my report to that or I could if
I wanted to let's just uh do that here.
If I wanted a slicer instead, we don't
have really have slicers in our reports.
That's a design principle. But let's say
I wanted to add a slicer here for
customer group for that dimension. Let's
just get that um up here. And
let's just center this down here
like this. And
uh like this. Then I could put in
customer group into that. And now you
see the global dimensions. The global
dimension one is also present here. So
what is the dynamic part of this? Let's
go back to business central and uh and
change our dimension setup. So if I now
open our general
ledger setup where we set up the
dimensions for our GL. You can see here
our global dimension one and two um or
global dimension one uh two and uh I
have shortcut dimensions here as well.
If I add say business group as a
shortcut dimension three let's see how
we can get that into PowerBI. So now I'm
going to shift back to PowerBI desktop
and show you that. So back here in
PowerBI desktop, I now choose to refresh
not the full data set but just the
dimension sets here with a schema and
data refresh. And it will just take a
few seconds. And let's see what happens.
We are syncing. We are loading. And now
we are almost done. Done.
So
working on it. And there we go. Now we
have business group name as a new like
table here. That means I could actually
take the business group uh here instead
of the customer name and then I could
start using that as a filter if I had
any data for business group there.
Right? So that's how dynamic dimensions
work. Let's just go and wrap up and
we're done. If you want to know more
about PowerBI in Business Central or
anything analytics, this is the AK link
you need to go to in our learn
documentation aka.ms/bcan
analytics.
Um, remember to follow the product group
here on LinkedIn. We have an aka link
for that aka.ms/bc
LinkedIn. This is where you get weekly
news from the product group on anything
related to business central. And uh
you're probably watching this on
YouTube. That means you might know that
we also have a YouTube channel from the
product group. We have more than just
these watch new. We also have um
co-pilot and AI tips and tricks, deep
dives, and even under the hood podcasts
where you get uh like a sneak peek into
new features uh months, sometimes months
before they actually hit the release
plan. So, ak.ms/bc
YouTube is uh the link that you should
be using to to uh to bookmark us or or
follow us on YouTube.
And uh then uh if you're a business
central partner um the aka link
aka.ms/bcall
is uh the only thing you need to to
bookmark that gives you all the other
aka links relevant for you. Of course if
you are a business central partner make
sure that you are on yammer. So um that
is the network for all partners no
customers there where you can ask
questions or discuss the product both
with your fellow peers and also with the
product group engineers and program
managers. Finally both for partners and
for customers the office hours is where
we on a monthly basis uh throw out a
topic. We'll uh we'll we'll discuss it.
there's a Q&A uh so go to the AK link uh
for that if you want to see the schedule
of the next office hours and uh and kind
of engage with the product group on the
the the future of Business Central. And
with that, we are done here. So um I'll
wish you a great day and hopefully see
you at some of the other launch edition
videos. Thank you.